GLORIA:
Whoa.
This is so beautiful.
Wow.
That's a good price.
Mom, can we leave soon?
I'm tired.
I was at school all day.
I don't know what you gonna do
when you get a real job.
You said school is my job.
Boy, shut up.
I'm almost done.
Wow.
("Give Me One Reason"
by Tracy Chapman playing)
* Give me one reason
to stay here *
* And I'll turn
right back around *
* Give me one reason
to stay here *
* And I'll turn
right back around *
* Said I don't want
to leave you lonely *
* You got to make me
change my mind *
* Baby, I got your number *
* Oh, and I know
that you got mine *
* But you know
that I called you... *
Mom, can I get this shirt?
-This one, in my hand.
Better not have
no craziness on it.
No.
Oh, why you had
to pick this color?
This is the only one.
Let me see it.
* Call me anytime... *
Thanks, Mom.
Oh, don't thank me yet.
You're gonna work for it.
Go and get me a bag
of potato chips.
-The kind with the owl on it.
Over there, by the jeans and
the socks and the other snacks.
Go on and find it, boy.
GLORIA:
Earn?
You better be up, in there.
I am.
* Here comes
the brand-new flava in ya ear *
* Time for new flava
in ya ear... *
EARN:
What's up?
Chillin'.
Cool shirt.
Thanks.
You do the math homework?
I forgot about it.
Just copy it during lunch.
Hey, who did that?
Huh?
I said, who did that?
Aw.
Hey, man, I'm sorry, though.
-I didn't mean to...
-Yo.
You threw that yogurt
out the window?
Yeah, listen, I'm sorry.
DRIVER:
No moving around the bus.
BOY: Every single time, you're
always like, "No, stop it."
:
That doesn't even make no sense.
-You know, you know.
CHRIS:
Oh, snap.
Look at the nigga
with the FUBU shirt.
Yo, man, let me see.
Man, do I want one of these.
I got to wait
till my birthday, though.
MARK: Oh, Earn out here,
he trying to jump fresh.
I see you.
You know.
MARK:
Okay. I got you.
So, what-what you telling me is,
y'all finna be mad at me for
the rest of the time I'm here...
Hey, Earn.
I like your shirt.
Thanks.
It's new.
MARK:
Wait, wait, wait.
Y'all had a sale, or something?
Why both y'all
got the same shirt?
CHRIS:
Oh, shit!
One of y'all got a fake shirt.
Look, this one has more stripes
than that one,
and that one got a patch.
Oh, no, y'all wearing
fake FUBU now?
My shirt ain't fake.
Talk to Earn.
My shirt ain't fake, either.
"My shirt ain't fake, either."
One of y'all got a fake shirt.
Let me see the tags.
-Same to me.
CHRIS:
I don't think he's here yet.
He wasn't on the bus,
so he might come late.
Definitely gonna know
which one fake.
MR. HALEY:
Okay, ladies and gents.
Let's take our seats.
I'm Mr. Haley, and I'm subbing
for Mrs. Fox's homeroom.
Why your shoes so dirty?
He got chicken grease
on his shoes.
Please take a seat, young man.
Your underarms smell like ribs.
Sit down right now.
I'm gonna write you up.
CLASS:
Oh...
Earthquake!
So, do you know why
you're here today, Alfred?
Racism. Not everybody's
gonna like me.
Well, no, that's not it.
Waleed came here today
because he believes
you stole
his graphing calculator.
Hmm. Racism.
He did steal my calculator.
I know he did.
-No, I didn't.
-He's lying.
I bought one from him.
It was the one that got stolen.
My name was already
engraved in it.
Prove it, 'cause that's a lie.
This is exactly
why we don't allow
the buying and selling
of any items
here on school property.
You definitely know
that, Alfred.
I've told you that
several times.
Well, if that was true,
then both of us are guilty.
You'd have to write me
and him up.
So do what you got to do.
Okay. Alfred, go back to class.
And if I hear about
you selling anything,
I'm gonna send you to I.S.S.
Got it?
I need a pass.
There you go.
Hey, they got snitches
up in here!
-MR. WHITMAN: Alfred!
I will write you up, boy.
Go to class!
Wait, so what's going on?
Devin has the exact
same shirt as me.
Well, pretty much.
One of 'em's bootleg, though.
-Fake.
So?
Your shirt looks fine to me.
But if it's fake,
everybody's gonna roast me.
Forever.
Remember how Thomas
got his nickname?
Who?
Thomas Jones.
Doo-doo Jones.
Oh. Yeah.
Well, is your shirt fake?
I don't know.
Doesn't seem like
a big deal to me.
I've worn this shirt
twice this week.
Beat your ass
with your hand-me-down overalls.
Gonna be major differences
between animal cells
and plant cells.
The cell walls, for instance.
So, when we're looking
under the microscope,
we are going to locate
the key differences.
Denisha.
Denisha, sit up.
You can't sleep here.
My head hurts.
MRS. BANKS:
Remember you said you were going
to do some work today?
DENISHA:
So?
Everybody, go ahead
and break into your lab groups.
Denisha, do we need to go
and talk outside?
No.
We talked about this
at the meeting.
Are we gonna have
a good day today?
I don't know. Are we?
This one's a plant cell.
Are you sure? I couldn't tell.
There's a chloroplast in there.
Hmm, I thought that was
a mitochondria.
You're pretty smart, Earn.
RACHAEL:
Look at this one.
The thing on the right
is a vacuole, right?
I think so.
Last one.
Yeah? Let me see.
You got a thread on your shirt.
Um... it's an animal cell.
All done.
Hey, yo, is that him?
That's him. Come on, come on.
-Come on, come on.
-Oh, sh...
-Hold up, hold up, hold up.
-Yo, yo, yo.
Oh, shit. Look at this.
Nigga, where did you get
this fake
A thrift store?
My shirt's not fake.
I got it at a regular store.
I don't...
My mom bought it for me.
BOTH:
Oh!
-Come here, come here.
-Hold on.
Look at him trying to hide
his fake shirt.
Don't try and hide that shit
now. It's too late, nigga.
My shirt's not fake.
Uh, I don't know, man.
It looks fake to me.
Hey, this nigga
ain't got on FUBU.
-He got "FEBE."
Hey! Hey, everybody!
-This man got on FEBE!
Like, type of nigga to wear
four-line Adidas and shit.
* Excuse me, do you think that *
* I might be able
to touch you? *
*
-* Yay-yay *
* I can tell you how I feel *
* About you night and day *
* How I feel about you *
* No, no *
* I can tell you how I feel
about you... *
What's up?
You got that homework?
Left it in my locker.
Everyone's talking about
you and Devin's shirt.
Yeah, I know.
People in other grades
know about it.
Well, your shirt is real,
so you ain't got
nothing to worry about.
Everybody's gonna roast
the hell out of Devin, though.
It's gonna be bad. You can't
wear no fake shit here.
Nobody knows
whose shirt is fake.
Johnny's not even here.
Yeah, he is. He came in late,
but he was in Ms. Wells' class
with me. He's here.
OLDER KID:
This fool got on FEBE, too.
Hey, look, look,
look, look, man.
So, tell me, whose is fake,
yours or little dude over there?
Man, my dad bought this for me.
All right?
I don't wear bootleg clothes.
I got all the Jordans,
everyone knows that.
And Earn come in here every day
looking like a bum,
so y'all know his shirt is fake.
Y'all know it.
My dad don't buy me
nothing fake.
: Hey,
you a funny dude, man, hold on.
-Hey, come here, nigga.
-Come on, brah.
Why you got to be like that?
Ooh, Rush Hour soundtrack.
:
Al.
Al. Alfred.
Nothing, really.
Hey, you saw that Dragon Ball Z
last night?
Nah, my mom won't
let me watch it anymore.
Saw the black guy
with the red lips
and now she says it's racist.
-Oh, yeah, man, that's weird.
-Yo. You got to help me.
Why, what's wrong?
It's my shirt.
Somebody has the same one as me
and now everybody's saying
one of us has a fake shirt.
Oh, snap, man, that's you?
-Nothing.
-I was trying to be cool.
-Bruh.
Man, is this shirt bootleg?
I don't know.
I got it at Marshalls,
but it was on sale.
Man, that's why you can't be
buying stuff on sale.
Bro, you got to get some money.
He's tripping.
Look, there's a hole in it.
I'm serious, Al.
I need your help.
I'm not cool like you.
If the older kids find me,
they're gonna beat me up.
Yeah, man, you're right.
What should I do?
I'm freaking out.
Uh, how cool is the other kid?
He's pretty cool.
He always has dope clothes.
His dad is, like, 30.
Man, don't be acting nervous.
I mean, people try
to come at you, just deny it.
Confidence is the key.
All right?
Hold it down, cuzzo.
Heading to lunch.
Okay.
MRS. WILLIAMS: Make sure
you finish your packets
and bring them in tomorrow.
I'm going to place a bin
on my desk.
I want you to put them in there.
And cite your work, folks.
The Internet is not a source...
-All right,
names at the top
of your packets.
That's an easy 50 points.
Good job.
Wait, Earn!
Johnny? Guess who I found.
Check it out.
Oh, this shit crazy.
Let me see the tag.
This one's fake!
It says "made in Bangladesh."
It should be China.
I knew he was wrong as hell.
Hey, yo, his shirt fake, y'all!
Yo!
Hold up, hold up,
hold up, hold up, hold on.
Let me see.
Man, this one the real shirt.
It's supposed to say "made in
Bangladesh" on this one.
Of course this fool gonna say
"made in China." He is Chinese.
-Come on, man.
That one the fake one.
Trust me, I know.
Man, my shirt ain't fake.
It ain't.
CHRIS:
Yo, this nigga homeless!
Devin rockin' fake FUBU now.
JOHNNY:
I'm not Chinese. I'm Filipino.
Wait. Here you go, Earn.
You know, that's my number,
if you want to call me.
But only between 6:00 and 9:00.
O-Okay, cool.
-See you tomorrow, Earn.
-See ya.
Yo. I can't believe this fool
tried to lie on you.
Yeah, it's crazy.
Yeah, 12th-graders
just found out.
They're going in on this man.
-Damn.
Hey, FEBE, man.
OLDER KID: You finna cry
or something
("Passing Me By" by The Pharcyde
playing)
GIRL : Band practice
will be moving to Room G today
due to a leak in the ceiling.
That is Room G.
Just a reminder,
the book fair is this Tuesday.
If you have any books
you want to donate,
you can trade them
with Mr. Johnson...
Spirit Week is next week.
We will be doing Pajama Day,
Sports, Crazy Hair,
and '80s Day...
Everyone, please settle down.
I came to let you all know
something very serious.
Your classmate, Devin Myers,
committed suicide last night.
We're not sure why,
but we've heard
a couple of things.
It seems Devin's parents
had just gotten divorced,
and he was dealing with it
pretty hard.
Now, if anybody needs to talk
about what happened,
please visit Mrs. Lindell
in the counselor's office.
Mrs. Banks or any other teacher
will write you a pass.
Thank you, Mrs. Banks.
MRS. BANKS:
I think it's good to remember
that we all have
personal things going on
in our life
that other people may not
know about.
So...
-Hi, Mrs. Banks.
-Oh, hello, Denisha.
MRS. BANKS:
But... let's try to be
more understanding
of one another.
Okay, um, turn to page 45
in your books.
And, uh, who wants to read?
-I'll do it, Mrs. Banks.
-Okay.
Whenever you're ready.
Hey.
You look tired.
No, I'm okay.
Just a long day.
Maybe you need to start going to
bed sooner and stop staying up.
Hey, Earn.
-Hey, Auntie.
GLORIA:
I got a call from the school.
One of your classmates died.
-Yeah, Devin.
-Hmm.
-Kind of.
That's so sad.
She seemed to think
maybe some of the older boys
were messing with him.
You better say something
if somebody tries harassing you.
People will bully you
your whole life if you let 'em.
-Yeah, they will.
-You got to stand up
for yourself.
Mm-hmm, and you and your cousin
got to look out for each other.
You guys look out
for each other, now.
Boy, get your feet
out that chair.
GLORIA: You start
piano lessons tomorrow.
-Yeah, I'm ready.
I'm gonna lay out
a suit for you,
so you'll need to add
a black belt.
A suit?
Why I got to wear that?
Because I said so.
You want to make
a good impression.
Our mother always said,
"You got one chance to make
a first impression."
LORRAINE:
Mm-hmm. True indeed.
But it's gonna be all hot...
GLORIA:
I don't care.
You are a black man in America,
and when you meet people,
you need to look good.
Your clothes are important.
That's true, Earn.
You need to wear the suit.
GLORIA:
Oh, and I got you another one
of those FUBU shirts.
It was on sale.
Don't say I never did
anything for you.
Thanks.
* Ooh, ooh, ooh *
* Ooh-ooh-ooh, ooh-ooh-ooh *
* Ooh-ooh-ooh, ooh *
* Ooh, ooh, ooh-ooh-ooh *
* Life *
* I wonder *
* Will it take me under? *
* I don't know *
* Imagine smokin' weed
in the street *
* Without cops harassin' *
* Imagine goin' to court
with no trial *
* Lifestyle:
cruisin' blue Bahama waters *
* No welfare supporters,
more conscious of the way *
* We raise our daughters *
* Days are shorter,
nights are colder *
* Feelin' like life is over *
* These snakes strike
like a cobra *
* The world's hot, my son
got knocked *
* Evidently, it's elementary *
* They want us all gone
eventually *
* If I ruled the world *
* Imagine that *
* I'd free all my sons *
* I love 'em, love 'em, baby *
* Black diamonds and pearls *
* If I ruled the world *
* I love 'em, love 'em, baby. *
Captioned by
Media Access Group at WGBH